[Music]
[Applause]
welcome to the high existence podcast
where we challenge the way you live we
bring you the wisdom and tools to help
you grow into a more enlightened version
of yourself join us by taking the
ultimate life experiment I have 30
challenges to enlightenment course a
complete spiritual path to help you
overcome the limitations of your mind
and to embody the highest philosophical
realizations use the code wisdom a check
out to get a huge twenty five percent
off the course available only to podcast
subscribers at store a existence calm
I'm your host John Waterlow you can find
me over on high existence and on my own
podcast voices in the dark hi everyone
welcome to the high existence podcast
before I introduce the guest I just want
to circle back to the pre-recorded promo
there that you just heard about the
thirty challenges to enlightenment I
know pre records aren't always the most
exciting way to hear about something I
want to recommend it myself just on a
personal level because it's something
that I actually read and worked on
whilst I was spending a month in a
Buddhist monastery and a hilltop in
Nepal and believe it or not just by all
the teaching all the other reading I was
doing it was actually just the handbook
that goes with that course that was
maybe the most profound insightful and
life-changing thing that I experienced
worked on and thought about during that
month the boys who put it together the
high existance team did an incredible
job of pooling together all of their
knowledge self growth experience and put
it in this format which you can really
directly apply into your life and it not
only gave me a lot of insight into
myself but it showed that so much of
what I was learning in the monastery via
Buddhism is something that goes beyond
any particular school of thought from
Joseph Campbell to Nietzsche to
psychology books to other self-help
manuals a lot of them are kind of saying
the same thing in different language and
then the 30 challenges course you get it
pulled together and you begin to see he
finds the ways in which the message can
connect to you through the different
modalities that they pull in and I
definitely recommend you go check it out
and with 25% off with that code it's a
really great opportunity
and I think there's a free version a
little sampler booklet so you can take a
look and see for yourself
see if it is something that you think
would connect for you anyway moving
swiftly on our guest this week is Daniel
SH macton Berger of the neuro hacker
collective if you haven't heard our
first episode with Daniel you can go
check it out on the feed if you want to
hear more about the macro-level the fate
of humanity from ecological economic
perspectives what new systems do we need
to put in place if we want to preserve
our world and ourselves as a species
Daniel could be introduced in so many
different ways as a philosopher a great
thinker a strategist someone who can
deal as easily with talk about quantum
mechanics as he can about the human body
and systems that draw the world together
and make it function in this particular
episode we're talking about how we can
make change at the level of you and me
we talk about health and it's not just a
kind of biohacking podcast that we do
talk about neuro hackers principal first
big product called qualia which is a
nootropic there isn't like most
nootropics that give you a little buzz
and then kind of screw up your system
qualia is actually specifically made to
raise the baseline of the human
regulatory systems making you more able
to deal with everything in your life
down from the biological level up to the
consciousness level is how we experience
things if you want to try qualia we do
have a deal with the neuro hacker
collective and you can go to the show
notes click that you get a 10% off offer
using the code hi existence
my time has tried it out and says it's
absolutely phenomenal for him it allows
a huge amount of mental clarity but
beyond that as you'll hear in this
episode it's doing so much more to help
you be the best version of yourself but
why is it that's kind of the theme of
this episode we talked about how given
that we are physically embodied
everything that we do is mediated
through our biology and therefore we
have a responsibility to ourselves and
to the world everything that we do to
understand that so that we can actually
be that version of ourselves put the
work out do things that help us connect
with other people and the world around
us but most of us we don't really know
how our body works and we don't have
practices and thought processes which
help us to do that
Daniel unpacks things down at the level
of the the key pillars the foundations
that we need to put in place in order to
be able to be the versions of ourselves
that we most want to be so we dig into
those foundations there's lots of
practical advice in this on how to alter
your life and effectively upgrade
yourself but we also reflect on how
difficult this is to do and to overcome
that resistance in a world or at least
in our Western societies in which the
medical system is essentially set up to
treat acute problems without really
getting down to what's causing them
which can be as simple as a nutrient or
mineral imbalance he breaks that down in
language that's so much easier to
understand than the kind of deep science
that he's actually drawing on and has a
significant amount of command over
talking about Daniel is something that I
could do at enormous length and so I'm
going to cut it short here and let him
speak for himself this is an incredible
episode and from a very wise man that
was a real privilege for me to speak to
I know you're gonna love it
and if you have questions he invites it
at the end that he's happy to come back
on the show and answer questions
directly then email me I think it's
probably the easiest thing to do and the
address is J Waterlow that's J wate RL
OWA at high existence com let me know
what your questions are for Daniel will
collect some together and see when we
can get him on next time and address
those directly now please enjoy the
episode hey welcome back
Daniel shhhhh macton burger to the hi
existance podcast this is part 2
strongly advised if people want to hear
about the future of the world that they
go and listen to the first part where we
took a really macro view of where we are
as humanity and where we may be going
next and in this part we're going to
dive more into the personal development
the bio hacking the neuro hacking and
how we can develop our cell
in order to do anything positive in the
world Daniels founder @ neuro hacker
collective which is a movement dedicated
to upgrading our individual and
collective capacities and to
safeguarding the well-being of all as
you would hear in the first episode it's
pretty pretty tricky to sum up Daniel
though I guess is pretty tricky to sum
up anyone in a in a fair and rounded way
and we had a really great conversation
so welcome back and looking forward to
this second part thanks for having me
it's good to be back I really enjoyed
our last conversation so to begin in the
giving we've already got I guess if
there were any soft questions in the
first one we had them in the first one
so we can dive right into the bigger
picture here we'll talk about qualia
which is the nootropic that have been
that's been developed by the neuro
hacker collective which is having
incredible results for many people
Martin who joined this last time was
sharing some of his own experiences
which were very positively found it very
powerful and so we'll get into that but
first at the more general level the
personal level there's a theme in your
work and it's something that a lot of
people who read how existence really
resonate with it's the idea of taking
responsibility for ourselves before we
can do anything for others
what does responsibility mean to you and
what do you think are the first steps
that anyone needs to take in terms of
personal responsibility and how perhaps
it's the first step is admitting that we
haven't been doing so how do we make
that first the first step to to find
that truth mmm-hmm well in this context
more talk about our own physical and
mental and psychological and spiritual
health and well-being ultimately if a
doctor does a good job or messes up with
a procedure or with a drug
recommendation or whatever with our
health we're going to be the ones who
benefit or suffer from it
and so we're more invested in the
medical care and the psychological care
and the health that we get than anyone
else's and so it's really a
responsibility we want to take to
understand our system well enough that
even to the degree we're interacting
with professionals that we understand
what they're saying we understand the
alternatives we understand the
consequences we understand that you know
risks and upside ratios and if we don't
and we just kind of trust an authority
to know everything about a topic and
always make good decisions for us and
then just be mad at them when they don't
it's just not a very empowered approach
and you know as soon as you realize that
we're already in an exponential
information ecology where you've got so
many journal articles coming out on any
new topic and a clinician is a busy
person that's having to mostly see
people they can't stay up-to-date with
what is new and relevant and there's so
many kind of key breakthroughs I don't
know in the different European countries
that your listeners are in what the
stats are but in the United States right
not iatrogenic disease meaning disease
that is caused by the practice of
medicine so interactions from drugs and
complications complications from surgery
infections about in the hospitals etc is
depending upon what you include in that
is either the first leading cause of
death in the US or the third and so Wow
it's a big deal for people to realize
that and even the people who aren't
dying are mostly you know they are
experiencing side effects from other
meds or treatments they're on or they
just have sub-optimal quality of life
because the medical system is mostly not
oriented towards optimizing human
flourishing its oriented towards
treating acute illness and
so if we want to have a really richly
flourishing life in all dimensions there
are causal dynamics that are associated
with health that we can actually
progressively understand better and
there are choices that we can take they
make a huge difference from the
foundations of how we sleep and eat and
move and process stress and information
to what we actually engage in in terms
of life extension integrative medicine
you know personalized medicine factoring
or genomics etc yeah I think if anyone
has had more than just a common cold and
they've they've been to their doctor
it's it can be kind of shocking I've had
it a few times where you rapidly realize
that you've the limits of current
medical knowledge at least in terms of
when you go to a doctor you brush up
against them surprisingly quickly and
the a lot of I guess it's part of the
convenience of seeing so many people
they're trying to push you into a
flowchart
of expected situations and going okay
well you've mentioned this symptom so
I'm going to need to prescribe you this
and that's kind of the end of the story
here I had a a junior doctor friend of
mine who gave me some cause for hope who
said that here being taught the patients
know their condition better than you do
and you should listen to them because
they also know the history better than
you do
and can tell you how how things have
gone but even with that more open mind
you're suggesting we need to do some of
the work ourselves and go looking but
there's you know if you type almost any
set of symptoms into Google you're gonna
see a fairly scary and bunch of
misinformation mostly how can we try and
understand and what is the thing that we
should be trusting when we go looking
for it ourselves
yeah let's understand the problem space
a little bit better and then let's
understand how people can approach
empowered responsibilities well so you
said there are limits of knowledge let's
not even get to the limits of knowledge
first let's just look at the limits of
time so then way that modern medical
system in most developed nations the way
the financial structure of it works
doctors just can't afford to spend much
time with people unless it's a concierge
in practice where people are paying a
huge amount of out-of-pocket money
because that doctor racked up a
tremendous amount of student loans in
the process of learning medicine that
they have to pay back and etc right so
they if it if a doctor's seen you for
five minutes or 15 minutes and sometimes
two minutes for a health issue and
sometimes a complex health issue it's
not even the limits of knowledge that
are gonna be bumped up it's the limits
of time to be able to get enough data I
have a I have a doctor friend here I
actually think is one of the most
knowledgeable integrative
rheumatologists in the world and really
has a profound understanding of causes
of autoimmune disease but as a result
his clinic got so inundated with
incurable cases that came that he
started having shorter and shorter
sessions and then I started watching him
actually practice really poor medicine
because he only had a minute with each
person and so we didn't even get to ask
the questions that would give him a
holistic picture again so the first
thing you can be pretty sure of is that
if your doctor isn't getting a really
good sense of your whole medical history
and your symptom ology and when your
symptoms started and how that correspond
to different exposures and events that
might have happened and looking at
really you know good laboratory data and
corresponding and seeing that it makes
sense they just couldn't possibly have a
decent picture of what to do yeah I
think my doc did I try and hold on to
even as I move around the place what I
like about him as he's always running
late and he's running late because he
tries to give people the time that they
need but obviously there's knock-on
consequences for him all right so then
let's explore this a little further
conventional medicine modern Western
allopathic medicine has done a brilliant
job of saving a tremendous amount of
lives from things that we used to die
from that are mostly acute onset illness
and it's it's really an exceptional
system of medicine for acute cause
suffering so if we're talking about
injury it's not that we can't do a lot
better in the future and we will but
anybody who gets in a car accident or
gunshot would much rather go to the ER
than any other healing system and if you
have acute poisoning so dealing with
toxicity that is acute high level
toxicity or acute infection it's really
good at dealing with all that if you
have chronic complex illness that did
not come on from one acute cause so
we're looking at cancer we're looking at
autoimmune disease we look at
neurodegenerative diseases we're looking
at psychiatric disorders it's
interesting to know that there's pretty
much no actual cures for any of those
there are symptom treatments and of
course if someone's body is running a
cancer we can cut it out we can radiate
it out we can poison it out and it's
chance of coming back depending upon the
kind of cancer is fairly high because we
didn't actually understand why the body
is growing cancers there in terms of why
are cancer cells proliferating more than
normal and why did the body's immune
response not know how to deal with them
effectively it's actually only in the
last year or two with the proliferation
of immunotherapy is that cancers
actually starting to be looked at in a
causal way at all chemotherapeutics
radiation and surgery the only things
that have been approved are exclusively
symptomatic without addressing why the
body's doing this same is true with all
of those all those disorders and so one
of the reasons is that we we don't have
a good type of science for understanding
in a very complex system like the human
physiology how dis regulation works it's
not acute if it's acute it's kind of
easy to tell they got exposed to this
poison
and they got sick instantly they got it
they you know ate this sushi and they
got food poisoning another sick that's
kind of straightforward but in there are
some things where we have pretty good
correlation like someone has you know /
eats way too much carbohydrate and we
see type 2 diabetes come on there's
still a pretty straightforward
correlation but with the other diseases
that I mentioned they're more complex in
origin it's because one the cause and
effect are very separate in time we have
time dilation which makes it very tricky
to you have many different causes that
are contributing to the disease
oftentimes so it's not actually that
there is one thing that was wrong it
might have been some nutrient
deficiencies and it's actually really
important to talk about this for a
minute when we think of nutrient
deficiencies in modern nutritional
Theory related to modern medical theory
we think of again an acute level of
deficiency such or a level of deficiency
such that it causes that a acute disease
so if item NC being so low that you get
scurvy or vitamin b1 being so low you
get berry berry well if you look at
where an optimal level of that vitamin s
versus where the level is at which you
get an acute disease is a pretty big
range in between there of suboptimal
levels right it's not low enough yet to
be a disease state but it's pretty far
from where an optimally healthy person
is yeah this is ICU in terms of
diagnosis right and so there's a lot of
subclinical deficiency that doesn't show
up as deficiency because in a disease
model it's not yet causing an acute
disease but that doesn't mean that it's
not causing the regulatory processes of
the body that are supported by that
particular nutrient to regulate less
well well if it's regulating less well
you can start having you know all kinds
of sub adequate regulation occur Dickens
evangeline tube disease the same is true
with subclinical toxicity
so someone can have a cute let exposure
or mercury exposure where they get sick
right away and it's really obviously
sick you can look at what the ideal
level is which is there's no mercury at
all there's a pretty big layer in
between which is a much higher amount of
mercury or lead or cadmium or PCBs or
styrenes or whatever life is eight that
would have been there in an evolutionary
environment but not yet enough of a
level that we would call it an acute
poisoning or toxicity but it has an
effect as it sometimes massive
biological effect as a carcinogen or a
neurologic disruptor or an occurring
disrupter and so now imagine that we
start stacking these right now imagine
that we recognize that in the United
States and I imagine it's similar in
with a pretty big variance actually in
different developed nations when we look
at the breast milk mothers in the United
States and not mothers in industrial
areas but randomized areas we find in
the vicinity of 200 different
petrochemicals in the breast milk and
this is things like volatile organic
compounds from carpet and paint as well
as you know styrenes from the memory
foam bed as well as things like
organophosphates from the herbicides
that are used in agriculture to you know
things that come from industrial
manufacturing and etc and those all have
effects so now you look at a world where
or agriculture depletes the topsoil of
minerals and so we and then we only put
back in with our fertilizer just a few
main minerals right we put NPK back in
but we remove all of the 70 to give or
take trace minerals so then we get trace
mineral e deficient topsoil and the
vegetables still look like vegetables or
the feed that goes to the livestock
still looks like what it is but it's
missing really key nutrients that are
parts of enzymatic process etc so we
have you know kind of
Vick Witness nutrient deficiency as a
result of agriculture that is not
regenerative to the topsoil while
simultaneously having adequate exposure
to chemicals that were not part of our
evolutionary environment and it's kind
of an important understand like the
detox systems of the body that in detox
is kind of a bad word because it's been
so abused by fad diets but it's a real
thing that your cells are producing
metabolic outputs which are the toxin
the toxic output of the metabolism and
the body gets rid of them the kidneys do
that the lungs do that the liver does
that as lymphatics are involved etc the
exhaling co2 is doing that so our body
has detox astons for dealing with things
that were in its evolutionary
environment but glyphosate was not in
our evolutionary environment right and
neither was like any significant amount
of refined heavy metal and so we don't
even have good evolved mechanisms to
deal with those things so when you start
looking at multiple different types of
subclinical chronic toxic exposures and
deficiencies and psychological stress
and pathogens and again I'm not talking
here about acute pathogenic exposure
meaning you have a flu or meningitis I'm
talking about dysbiosis in the gut and I
think now most people are probably
pretty familiar that there are a huge
number of interactions outcome well
actions that are necessary to make human
health that human cells don't do that
are symbiotic microbiome does and in an
evolutionary environment the baby always
got the genome of the mom and dad but it
also got the microbiome of the mom in
particular and so the microbiome and the
genome were passed down together genome
does not actually code everything
necessary to do a human well 80% of our
gob was produced in the gut main
anti-anxiety neurotransmitter give or
take 50% of our dopamine is produced
bacteria in the gut give or take 50% of
serotonin produced by bacteria in the
gut vitamin D binding protein that
actually is what makes vitamin D able to
go into the vitamin D receptors mostly
produced by a specific bacteria in the
gut so in evolutionary environment again
we didn't have antibiotics now this
doesn't mean antibiotics haven't save
losses lives of course they had but then
you also throw off and chlorine has
helped us in sanitation tremendously
save lots of lives but then chlorinated
water is also having an effect so you
know some people have there's so many
different like ways in which to like
pick up and go with these these
different points that you're making and
like like the the over focus on hygiene
that potentially leads us to not having
the kind of immune responses we need or
c-sections meaning the babies are not
getting yes the microbiome yes of the
mother and so on but the what the main
thing clanging in my head right now is
this is this is kind of scary there's
the general genuinely scary and to
circle back to the question that I asked
just a couple of minutes ago is how can
we find the trustworthy information to
be able to make inform steps because it
seems like it's a full-time job to try
and be on top of it and there's so and
when it's at the the below the threshold
where it's a condition that people can
clearly say oh you you've got this issue
isn't there a big danger that we just
run around imagining that we've got this
deficiency this deficiency this
deficiency and we're just kind of
guessing and we don't really know yeah
so the just in kind of wrapping the
major point I was trying to bring there
is that when it comes to disease that
doesn't have an acute cause oftentimes
it doesn't have one cause at all it
might be the dysregulation of regulatory
systems from exposure to toxins exposure
to pathogens dysbiosis in the garden
chronic stress
postural issues lack of movement
efficiency and you have one thing that
is suboptimal that makes the system
regulate slightly less well that makes
it more susceptible to other things that
are suboptimal you get a vicious cycle
and eventually there's enough
dysregulation that you actually start to
get damaged in certain tissues or
certain systems and those cluster
together and we call it a disease we
call it MS or rheumatoid arthritis or
whatever but the reason that we haven't
had good cures is because we're not
gonna find a single cause for we find a
number of different things that
statistically correlate but none of them
statistically correlated enough that
treating that one statistical
correlation always cures it because
that's one of a set of a number of
things that can be involved in it's not
even the same set in everyone so this is
a key thing in terms of understanding
why we have to take a more complex
approach to understanding something as
complex as a human body when you're
trying to understand issues like aging
and issues like chronic disease and on
the other side human flourishing
variable isolation right what is the one
thing that is wrong when one drug that
will treat it it's just not gonna work
so that's it that's important just kind
of from an approach point of view so how
do we find good resources and how do we
approach this well couple things like
all areas there's a pretty good Pareto
principle at 80/20 kind of principle
here where if people do a good job with
the foundations of well-being they're
going to have a lot less disease in
their life and the foundations of
well-being are relatively
straightforward so in order
sleep enough and sleep well that's a all
the regeneration that happens in the
physiology any nutrients that you take
in their ability to actually support the
genesis of new tissues etc any exercise
you do the ability for those tissues to
regenerate all of that's gonna happen
during sleep mostly during Delta sleep
so sleeping enough and sick and well
foundational eating just as a side note
before we get to the the next the next
part there there's such a cult these
days I think about the highest
achievement achievers in the world go on
for hours sleep and is yeah I wonder
about that like how are they managing to
continue to function and or do some
people only need four hours sleep yeah I
know a lot of world-class high achievers
and almost none of them have four hours
sleep most of them actually do a pretty
good job of self-care there are people
who will push very hard for a period and
then burn out and then they're either
done with their creative time period or
they have to learn a new way of being
there are people genetically who need
less sleep there's a few genes that
actually code for more efficient sleep
but this is actually a tiny percentage
of the population that can that will end
up needing in the vicinity of five hours
sleep
most people genetically do best on
something in the vicinity of eight hours
sleep there's a whole lawn it sleeps a
very complex topic in general how do you
know if you've slept enough and slept
well that you would wake on your own
feeling well-rested and energized and
you have good energy throughout the day
now obviously that's oversimplified
because your energy throughout the day
is gonna suck even if you slept well if
your blood sugar is unstable or if you
are not exercising which is a key to
circulation and generating androgens and
things that are necessary but if you are
waking tired
then there's then sleep is not
sufficient yet right so it's deep topic
we could do a whole thing on sleep over
at our site neural hacker we have up we
have a couple whole podcast just on
sleep with you know world-class sleep
researchers and there's a lot of sleep
tech that's coming out we're in the
process of developing some products for
sleep optimization but that's one of the
found
Pilar's okay the other foundational
pillar is like everybody knows these but
most people have not studied them well
enough to know how to optimize them like
sleep making sure that you aren't
exposing yourself to blue light and
stimulants in the last little while that
you're not exposing yourself to things
that have your mind anxious that you do
something to relax your body whether
it's a hot shower or a hot bath or some
stretching before bed that you create a
sleeping environment that is dark that
it doesn't get disturbed by noise so it
has a wait noise generator if needed
where you're not being disturbed
unnecessarily like there's a whole bunch
of practices
so it's both learn these practices and
implement them or deal with the
consequences of not having done it which
will end up looking like going to
doctors for illnesses later the next one
is movement and there's a whole lot to
get into in terms of what fully optimal
movement looks like you can check out
real movement specialists like Paul
check and IDO portal who will you know
teach you about the difference between
strength training and balance training
and coordination training and endurance
training and why it's important to
develop different patterns of movement
that stimulate neurogenesis but in which
genes get up regulated by different
kinds of exercise in which brain regions
get stimulated but again there's an
80/20 even for exercise which is if you
are getting your heart rate up near its
maximum for some period of time even a
short period of time daily you're gonna
do a lot better than if you don't and if
you break up being sedentary meaning you
aren't sitting for multiple hours on end
without movements you get up every hour
and do a few jumping jacks it doesn't
have to be a lot your life will be
radically better than if you don't your
health will be radically better and
again then study more because those who
exercise not just more but better really
will have a radically higher quality of
life you drop body fat percentage and
you dropped all cause mortality etc diet
is the next one which is as much as you
can take in foods that look like parts
of your evolutionary environment meaning
things that are not highly processed and
as much as you can avoid things that are
highly processed that's the good first
rule of thumb it's not perfect obviously
there are plants that are poisonous
obviously you can have a protein powder
that is processed that's actually good
for you
there's there's a lot of good books on
nutrition where you can dive deeper but
if you just start by thinking okay well
we evolved to have a diet that had a lot
of plants but not a lot of the same
plant right we would have had different
plants and different seasons and they
would have been a hunter-gatherer
environment been just little bits of
lots of different types all that have
different nutrients so can I do a
variety of different kinds of plants and
animal products and they should should
be organic it should not be covered in
pesticides meaning that if you spray a
chemical toxic enough to kill things
like ants and cockroaches on your food
and then eat it that's kind of silly and
should come from as well and maintain
soil as possible so if you can get even
better than organic if you can find
local farmers that do biodynamic farming
permaculture farming even better and as
much as it sounds like that's fancy all
it is is trying to get a little bit
closer to what all food was before the
Industrial Revolution it is it's it's
fancy exactly that it can be expensive
like I remember I live for a little
while in the US and I found it was
really expensive to try and buy things
that seem to be labeled organic or to
shop in Whole Foods I am I think it is
maybe a bit easier in some countries in
Europe and unless the labeling system is
misleading but there is is there kind of
a barrier of entry that's based on money
for a lot of people here No
yes going to Whole Foods can be
expensive there's a couple ways to look
at this one if you find your local
farmers markets because they aren't
having to pay to have a big-box store
with lots of I mean they're basically
disintermediating the grocery store part
you can get even fresher better quality
food cheaper and cheaper than what you
would pay for the conventional
agriculture at a normal store the
conventional produce so the cost really
can be dealt with the produce is usually
not that expensive the things that are
expensive in places like Whole Foods
usually are the healthy packaged foods
and pre-made foods the produce is a
little bit more expensive but it's still
like not super expensive and there's a
whole bunch of reasons why farmers
markets and coops are like really
valuable things to explore so that's one
topic on cost yeah it also sounds fun to
be able to to go there rather than just
be in another supermarket it is fun
you're supporting local farmers to
actually get paid better than they get
paid other places which and especially
the ones that are doing organic and
permaculture which supports
environmentalism in agriculture and
climate change dynamics and micro
economies and it's like this is just
every reason that's a good thing to do
and yes you can start to actually make
friends in the community there and have
this fun experience of what you know
markets have been for a lot of human
history so that's a way that cost is not
a barrier of entry the other thing
though is you know when we say solar is
more expensive than coal energy wise and
that solar still needs to get cheaper to
be at grid parity with coal in some
areas it's just complete nonsense
because 99% of the cost of coal energy
is just the coal company doesn't have to
pay for it so they don't internalize it
into the cost of coal it's externalized
to the Commons in the form of co2 and
mercury mercury vapor and nitrous oxide
and zinc oxide and the mountain
removal mining that it took to get it
and the like it there is a massive cost
to all people to the environment to
future generations to whatever that if
you had to say hey burn coal but just
don't leave the environments worse as a
result so whatever it takes to clean up
the effects in real time do that and if
it costs some money to do that you have
to include that in the cost of coal coal
would go up by the price of coal would
go up by hundreds or thousands of times
and solar would have been that grid
parity the moment it existed so and the
same is true in health care
I can eat shittier foods that are cheap
but there's a cost and it's a cost
that's being externalized to the
decreased health of my future and so
then I'm gonna have to pay the medical
and or just have a shorter or shittier
life and so it becomes important to
think about what does cost really mean
and what is actually worth investing in
right yeah so cost we can think of it's
not just a financial cost but there can
be the other and until I think it's a
it's a funny human thing that we tend to
ignore that sort of personal cost until
it actually hits us even though we have
all the evidence to see if you see
someone who smoked their whole lives and
didn't think about it then the cost
becomes evident later we say over and
over again but seem to have trouble when
it comes to ourselves humans suck at
this topic everywhere and it's why we
are so close to self-induced extinction
as a species which is short term gain
and long term expense and there's some
reasons why we suck at it is in and have
in our evolutionary environment pre
advanced technological capabilities we
just didn't have the ability to affect
our own feature negatively that much
it's
this is actually an important thing to
understand in our evolutionary
environment 250,000 years of being
homeless and something like 8 million
years of hominid history before the plow
and you know grains refined
carbohydrates etc for that whole time
period there was not an easy way to get
sugar fat or salt right sugar every once
while you'd find some berries but the
berries that we see today are radically
hybridized from the heirloom berries
back then that were like a few on a very
thorny bush for a very small amount of
time and you're in competition with the
birds right and and honey is a super
hard thing to actually deal with the
bees in that kind of world so are there
sugar there's such tiny little bits of
sugar the same is true with access to
salt in most environments and the same
is true with access to fats because you
know getting game every time you go out
after big game you can die in the
process of hunting with Spears and it's
mostly pretty lean meat right so
whenever we did have access to those
things they conferred so much
evolutionary advantage in terms of the
caloric density of fat and sugar made it
easier to live through a famine and the
ability of salt to replenish
electrolytes and elbows keep water on in
hot environments so we had a major we
evolved to have a strong dopamine
response when we would eat those foods
meaning as it's actually important to
get that those that had a stronger
dopamine response meaning a pleasure
reward circuit actually survived better
because they worked harder to go find
those foods and then they made it
through famines better right so we're
the descendants of the people that have
the strongest dopamine responses to
those foods now post-industrial
revolution we have made so much
abundance of sugar fat and salt but our
evolutionary genetic response to those
hasn't changed so now we're dying of
obesity rather than starvation and so it
was important to get that evolutionary
response of getting this major pleasure
head
when you eat sugar fat salt and ideally
all three together right like imagine
almost every fast-food meal if you do
the whole meal is all three of those
together and you get such a such a
dopamine flood that you become addicted
and you can't not eat it even though you
know that you are decreasing the quality
of your life in on every metric your
social life your sexual life your health
life your ability to generate finance
your emotional life everything as you
are doing that more and so we actually
had an evolved set of responses that
were appropriate to an environment and
then we became these amazing tool makers
and we changed our environment faster
than we could be genetically adapted to
so we have to actually know how to
navigate this built world that we've
made that is actually not a natural
environment to us still being the
genetic creatures that we are and this
is why those you know the two
marshmallow experiments of the kids that
had better delayed gratification and
impulse control doing better in every
area of life my impulse control ends up
being a really really big part of the
whole picture here but when you when you
look at the fact that natural selection
mostly selected for things that were
adaptive in the moment who ever could
you know not lose it that fight made it
through etc that's a short-term
orientation and we mostly couldn't do
things that damage the long-term that
much meaning overfish the entire ocean
or eat foods that would make us totally
ill chronically or and so we're in a
position now where when you look at
people's health and whether it's the
smoking situation you talked about or
the getting to exercise later and it
never happens or climate change or the
fact that we knew Fukushima was going to
have a earthquake five years before it
happened and nobody wanted to spend the
money this quarter on buffering against
it our orientation towards short-term
ease and short-term gain at probable
possible long-term expense is one of the
main things that if we want to survive
as a species and if we
have a good quality of life as
individuals we have to get past so if
you if listeners want to hear you know
biohacking secrets or heaps of
biohacking secrets that we can share
what ends up mattering like more than
any of those is being able to get good
at making decisions that are good from a
long-term focus yeah I think that's
something about the tyranny of the
quarterly financial report that is kind
of mirrors and maybe feeds back into on
the individual level that we think about
what I want now rather than what I want
in the future and if we if we want to
get into making better choices I want to
I want to talk about qualia the neuro
hackers flagship products sure real
quick one one more thing in that they
just want to share that I think I think
you guys will appreciate it one
application of VR tech that I thought
was really beautiful and it's it's in
development I don't know the name of a
company that's developing it but they're
doing VR avatars and so you have cameras
get the right pictures of you to render
you as an avatar then you can go into
the earth space see yourself as an
avatar and one of the things that was
done was age progression where you could
see a version of yourself as an older
person while you're a younger person but
it's actually you right like you're
looking in the mirror you lift your left
hand and you watch your hand move and so
you get a look at yourself as this older
person be like whoa that's me and then
it will do the age progression based on
how you're eating how you're exercising
if you're smoking etc and you can
actually watch the 60 year old version
of you look different habits the
yellowness of its teeth so the skin the
health of vitality that everything
looked different based on the lifestyle
habits based on real data of how those
things statistically work and one of the
things that happened in some of the
research was that as people were
relating with the older version of
themselves because right now the idea of
ourselves as older people is just a
completely abstract topic but us now is
totally real and visceral
and we feel or hunger now we don't feel
our fatness as an older person right or
our body pain or whatever it is and so
it's easier to make decisions based on
something concrete than something
abstract something that we're feeling in
real time versus something that you know
it's hard to actually even imagine a
relate with so as they were doing it
these people started making concretely
tangibly better choices for their
long-term life because they had a
clearer relationship with that being one
of them was actually financial that the
people today who were younger started
saving money more as they were relating
with their older avatar and another
one's health decision so even if you
don't have access to that VR just just
thinking about it hearing it can be
useful yeah I think that that personal
confrontation sounds really interesting
and I'm I'm finding just in myself
really it's making an impact on me to be
my early 30s to realize my body is not
working as well as it used to and to not
just kind of despair and accept that as
I think I know a lot of older people who
just go well you know that's how it is
you get older and everything hurts more
and things don't work so well but we can
actually make some differences we can
make some changes which can actually
affect us positively and I guess one of
the the main ones is that the conscious
input of better things into our bodies
in the way that you describe just in
terms of food but when it comes to the
world of biohacking which is ever more
widespread it seems to me there's
there's a lot to talk about by hacking
I'm like trying to formulate three
questions at once I guess it'd be better
to start by saying ask for like your two
minute description of what qualia is and
then we can really dig deeper into it
yeah so quality is a nootropic which
means some chemistry that enhances
cognitive function different aspects of
cognitive function beyond one's previous
baseline without causing negative side
effect that's the general best accepted
definite
nootropic there's different classes of
chemicals that are the primary classes
of nootropics that you know are
generally well studied and so this is
what a nootropic stack meaning a blend
of different chemical supplements that
affect different neurotransmitters
different pathways different aspects of
neuro chemistry and biochemistry to
enhance the underlying physical
substrate that supports cognitive
process and so why did we create it it's
the first of a bunch of products that
all have the same design philosophy and
methodology the next ones will be
launching early this next year but when
we started this we saw this kind of
meteoric exponential rise of the use of
smart drugs and specifically even
illegal off-label smart drugs we're
talking about adderall modafinil riddlin
vyvanse wellbutrin and mostly
dopaminergic but some some other
categories and we saw Averell do an
estimated five billion dollars in
illegal sales in the US per year when we
started smart drugs as a whole - about
15 billion dollars that's just
domestically right so internationally a
lot more and this is because people were
had such strong pressure to perform and
produce and really wanted to while
simultaneously having so much that was
damaging their ability to focus from all
of the social media kinds of
distractions to gut brain access being
out like we talked about where 50%
dopamine is produced and the nutrient
and deficiencies in toxicities and etc
and you know then other than people
going to off-label smart drugs we also
saw you know energy drinks where people
were doing 300 and 400 milligrams of
caffeine and
you know caffeine is a cool molecule
qualy has a very small amount of
caffeine and a unique form in it because
it's a really neat central nervous
system stimulant if we have caffeine
bound to an antioxidant from blueberry
skin called taro still being that
affects the pharmacokinetics of it so it
releases much slower so you don't get a
jolt and then a drop you get a very slow
central nervous system release over a
longer period of time but that is it
also helps the uptake of some of the
other more specifically active neural
chemistry but at those kinds of doses
this is really not a healthy
relationship with caffeine and you start
getting you know you'd get increased
focus and attention and alertness to a
certain point and then the jitteriness
and inability to focus starts getting a
negative response curve and a central
nervous system stimulant like caffeine
or a dopamine enhancer like adderall
are really only affecting a very narrow
range of the total aspects of chemistry
that are important for cognitive
enhancement and so one of the things
that you find is when people are going
to those kinds of solutions is that they
they work right like people are taking
them for their midterms or their finals
or their tech startup or for their
gaming or whatever because they actually
can focus better longer concentrate and
they have more motivation but one of the
things very interesting is some of the
other cognitive capabilities that you
would want online at the same time there
are studies that actually show they go
down so different aspects of memory like
total working memory goes down on that
role and creativity goes down and the
ability for fluid intelligence and task
switching goes down and it happens to be
that empathy goes down for most people
and irritability anxiousness
depersonalization go up and so that's
one problem is that it's a very narrow
set of positive effects the other
problem is that your body regulates
dopamine right your nervous system
regulates dopamine in a very kind of
Kampala
this way and you don't want fixed high
dopamine levels all the time you do want
your body to be able to up regulate its
dopamine when you're doing and dopamine
there's a kind of task like working on a
project and then you want it to be able
to chill when you want to go play with
your kids or cuddle or something else
and so rather than take a chemical that
externally exogenously overrides an
endogenous regulatory process and then
the process of doing that it actually
creates dependence and addiction which
most medicines that affect the brain and
mind end up doing we're much more
interested in understanding how the
regulatory process has worked and
providing chemistry that supported the
regulatory processes to be able to
regulate better so that you could
actually up regulate endogenous
regulatory capacity because we can
actually define health when we're
talking about disease earlier we can
actually define health as the robustness
of the regulatory capacity of the system
which means that any kind of issue can
come up any kind of deviation from homeo
dynamics and the system can actually
respond to it and so we wanted to work
on increasing the regulatory capacity of
the system so that rather than causing
addiction meaning the person was on it
for a while they get off and that were
screwed we wanted it to be that if
someone was on any product we made for a
while then they got off that they would
actually have lasting benefit in terms
of elevation of some positive functions
from the baseline before they started
and that's true for koala industry for
although other products that were making
its the design methodology and so with
quality the way we started was we said
okay when people are seeking cognitive
enhancement what are they really seeking
it's not just cognitive it's usually
emotional cognitive psychologic
energetic together right there they're
seeking focus and concentration and
attention those dynamics and memory the
ability for working memory to hold more
in their memory and their speed of
recall verbal fluency you know etc and
they want increased analytic
capabilities and synthesis capabilities
and creativity they also want to
increase motivation and dry
and emotional resilience and they also
want some complex things that are like
the dialectic of pretty opposite things
which is I want the ability to
concentrate really hard on one topic and
not get distracted while simultaneously
having the ability to task switch from
one thing to another thing what I need
to do that it's like we're asking for a
magic pill to fix everything here well
has nothing to do the magic pill it's
that a well regulated system is good at
shifting modes right like that's what
adaptiveness is and an adaptive creature
can go from sleeping to waking can go
from very different kinds of states and
the quicker that one can go between
different modes and the better they can
be in those modes as the adaptiveness of
the creature and so what we wanted to
support was the overall adaptiveness so
if we were just driving the chemistry of
focus and concentration
it would make task-switching worse we
could drive things that would support
task switching may focus worse to make
both better you have to not be exogenous
lis driving the chemistry in one
direction or the other but supporting
the regulatory processes and so this was
you know this is kind of at a high level
but this is our design philosophy for
how we wanted to approach anything in
the health and well-being space is let's
make sure that we are well and
specifically in the enhancement space
biohacking so often isn't looking at the
disease model but the enhancement side
and again modern medicine that's one of
the other differences is that it is a
disease model process so it's really not
looking at optimization so why we mapped
all those things to start was to say you
know people really don't just want to
increase focus well being more irritable
and less creative and with less code
Emery they want this whole suite of
things together that means that they
have increased creative productive
capacity and flow
and so then we said all right well what
do we know in any of the various
Biosciences human Biosciences about the
physiologic processes that mediate those
cognitive and subjective dynamics what
do we know about the neural chemistry
that mediates focus that mediates
task-switching
memory i/o etc and so we started to map
those processing some are acetylcholine
mediated right some have to do with the
nmda complex some have to do with how
catecholamines process some have to do
with sodium ion dynamic so we were
mapping these and saying how does the
body regulate those on its own can we
draw the regulatory processes and then
why does the body get less good at
regulating because of course kids
actually have this ability to focus on
something they're interested in and also
tasks which and fall asleep pretty
quickly and then be energetic right like
that's adaptiveness so starting to look
at why does why does a system have
decreased capacity to do those things
what are the rate limiting factors in
the system and what can we offer to
support the system's capacity to do that
better so like just as a for instance if
your listeners are interested in example
let's just say we take dopamine that
we're talking about earlier rather than
give you know something like an N feta
mean right at 11:00 p.m. feta mean it is
a enchained dopamine agonist where you
get a big rush of dopamine but it is
decoupled from changing acetylcholine
levels or glutamate or looking at how
the other catecholamines you're focused
or the neuro inhibitory chemicals or
anything else and it doesn't look at the
whole process of how the body normally
regulates dopamine so you do get down
regulation addiction we said well how
does the body normally do dopamine
creation and there's this whole complex
process of how protein is broken down
into amino acids and phenyl alanine is
converted and the tyrosine is converted
into an acetyl tyrosine is converted
into l-dopa crosses the blood-brain
barrier is kin
the dopamine travels down an axon
crosses the synapse has to cross a whole
bunch of different kinds of enzymes to
break it down into synapse and then goes
into one of multiple dopamine receptors
that affect how it's processed you have
to have the right dynamics happening in
the cell the Krebs cycle process is to
have enough energy to process that some
of it will hydroxylase into
norepinephrine you map this whole thing
out and then say how can we support each
step in that process and so then we have
you know what are the vitamins what are
the amino acids what of minerals were
the different dynamics convert one step
to the other step it can be at
suboptimal levels that lead to rate
limiting in those processes and so we
made a database of like 500 chemicals
that were associated with the underlying
physiology of all of those subjective
states and capabilities and then we
started paring it down in terms of which
ones are you know well tolerated and
have positive synergies with other ones
and don't have negative synergies and
support each step in the various
pathways and you know that led to an
initial hypothesis of how to make
something with things that we wanted to
test do we need more or less choline
donor in this more or less dopamine
agonist in here etc and that led to
about a hundred iterations with testing
and we gave qualia and we've done
preclinical tests where in clinical
trials now but we did preclinical is
preparing for the clinicals where we did
people's cue EEG brain scans as well as
a bunch of biometrics like HRV and
ethnography and etc and psychometrics
and cognitive metrics before people took
it and then once they did quality of
just once and then once they were on it
for a month and we saw really awesome
results the data set was too small we
only had that single blinded so I won't
speak to the numbers yet we're gonna
speak to him once the the full
double-blind did large larger scale
clinical trial comes out but you know
and we would of course have
dunh larger trials earlier on except
they're expensive and yeah trying to pay
for all of it is a tricky thing and this
is worth like we could have taken more
venture capital money earlier but then
we would have been more beholden to have
to maximize profits as per their goals
and we really wanted to do something
that we could really control with what
our own capacity to fund was so that we
could keep making the highest quality
things so like for instance our cost of
goods just the raw material costs for us
on this is more expensive than the
retail price of most metrics and it's
because being like you know we have a
versions of each ingredient like benefit
I mean version of be one for the effect
on peripheral neurons that we wanted is
something like a hundred times more cost
per kilo than if I mean that is the
normal form would be one that you could
put but we have those kind of expensive
forms because it was the one - that
should do what we wanted now we're
trying to get the cost down through
economies of scale but that was longer
than two minutes what we were trying to
do with quality and what it really is
clearly a super complex I mean even
beyond the super complexity of the
ingredients in there it's a very complex
and deep thinking approach that you've
taken so it kind of already sidesteps a
lot of the the reservations that people
have about biohacking and nootropics
where there tends to be some sort of
downside some kind of burnout element
which you've already said this is you
know from the foundation up is not what
qualia is about well I also wonder when
when I think and people I know who try
to take supplements to enhance their
performance one way or another it does
seem to still matter what it is that
they want to do when they take it so I
mean accrue a crude example can be you
could take modafinil fired a pretty
unhealthy relationship with modafinil
for much of a year a few a few years in
the past and after a time I realized but
I still kept doing it that I would take
it because I would
feel like I was on and I felt like I'm
great I'm doing great stuff I'm really
focused but if I really broke it down
and looked at it
I wasn't achieving anything you can take
it to get the sensation of being on it
but then do nothing so yeah it's is
there does this still play a factor in
in taking qualia because if you're if
you're just taking it but without any
sort of purpose in mind is that enough
it's a tool right and there is right use
of tools somebody can use a hammer wrong
and break their thumb or they can use a
hammer ray in buildings and so and to
the other point somebody can build
things that aren't worth building so
those modafinil towers that I built I
mean it's a classic thing where somebody
is using meth and there's just cleaning
their grout with a toothbrush because
they have a tremendous amount of energy
that needs to do something but they're
not really clear on whether the super
useful thing to do would be so if
someone already is sleeping well is
exercising well as meditating as dealing
with stress well has a empowering
outlook on life is clear on what they
want to create and then they add qualia
to that it's gonna be a much different
experience than if someone is thinking
in ways and living in ways that have
them aggressive and scattered and etc
and they take quality like that they're
not going to instantly just know what to
do with their lives because they have
some neurochemical support so in general
I would encourage people to do the
foundational things before I would have
them do any kind of more advanced
biohacking that said there's an
exception to that that I've seen which
is there are a lot of people who just
can't do the things they know will make
a difference for them there the habit
patterns the addiction patterns have
just been too strong they beat
themselves up for not exercising but
they just you know
many years of wanting to and it's still
not happening
and we've had a lot of people and I
can't make any claims about this but
we've had many people tell us that they
took qualia and then after years of
wanting to exercise and not they started
exercising or they started eating well
or they started doing things that they
actually felt that they had increased
energy and motivation and capacity to do
that they they were just overwhelming
and daunting previously and so yeah my
general recommendation we do the
foundational things first
unless there's difficulty with the
foundational things and you want to see
if this is an experiment that can
increase your capacity to do it yeah it
sounds a bit like some of the effects of
a regular meditation practice where you
certainly in my experience I end up
finding that there's more sort of space
and energy and capacity in myself to set
about doing things that I want to do but
usually provoke a kind of it feels like
fear I think quite often the onerous
task or it's like the kind of paradox of
procrastination in a way the thing the
is causing you so much stress and grief
you keep looking in the other direction
because it causes stress and grief and
yet the only way to change that is to go
and do the task it's kind of the
obviously later instinct is this is
related to that topic we're mentioning
earlier about delayed gratification so
there's the other side of that is facing
difficult things now and in general the
degree to which we can put off ease full
and pleasurable things till later and
face more difficult things now we will
have a more meaningful higher quality
and actually more pleasurable life this
is actually an important point let's
let's touch on this one little show
okay so I take the chocolate cake in the
moment and I'm getting a flood of
dopamine Erick responds to take this oh
good it feels awesome and I'm not
actually feeling myself increased
inflammation or store body fat or have
dysregulated blood sugar or whatever in
the moment I'm just feeling awesome
right tasting this and so in the moment
the chocolate cake is absolutely
increasing my pleasure but it is doing
those other things that I said and so
it's going to if I'm eating the
chocolate cakes more often I will have a
life with more inflammation more
unstable blood sugar which means lower
energy and mood issues and etc all of
which will lead to a life that has less
pleasure when you factor the entire
cause and effect set right right and
because having shitty energy and
unstable mood and inflammation is less
pleasure but then when your pleasure is
low you and you're feeling really shitty
then you crave anything that will make
you feel better again in the moment so
that that that's the addiction cycle
right and so in blood sugar is a classic
example you take something that spikes
your blood sugar you feel really good
but then it also crashes your blood
sugar then once your blood Sugar's
crashed you're kind of desperate and so
you will go for sugary things it will
raise it again when have you eaten
something that wasn't sugary earlier you
would have never had your blood sugar
crash in the first place and been stable
so the addiction cycle is a cycle of
hyper stimulus the dis regulates
baseline that leads to more desire for
hyper stimulus right yeah and it's
possible to have some of that attitude
towards exercise if you get on the
exercise wagon but then that also can
lead to an addiction the over exercise
because you're getting your kick but
probably still avoiding something
okay so I'll get to that in a minute but
let me tell the other part of this food
analogy because then we'll be able to
relate it so
let's say instead of the chocolate cake
I'm looking at eating a salad the salad
is not gonna give me the same dopamine
flood in the moment the chocolate cake
did even if it's a good salad right for
the fat sugar salt reasons we mentioned
earlier and that said as I'm doing the
salads regularly I will have a body that
is more mobile that has more energy that
has less fatigue that has less blood
sugar crashes it has less excessive
weight and that all translates to a body
whose baseline pleasure is higher right
and so the opposite of the addiction
cycle is something that does not spike
your pleasure
but that doesn't destabilize and
decrease your baseline and that leads to
slowly up regulating baseline and so
here's the the difference addictive
things spike your pleasure and then
crash it and then it spikes then it
crashes but the baseline lowers two
things you both get more highs and lows
and progressively more lows in the
addiction cycle in the healthy cycle
with anything you get less extreme highs
and lows and progressively more highs
right that's a kind of difference in the
relationship and so what's interesting
is while the addict is controlled by
pleasure they actually have much less
pleasure in their life right because the
baseline is is very different right and
so when we're talking about what is
healthy we're actually also talking
about what is more pleasurable
now you mentioned exercise and you
mentioned it as a addiction and also has
an avoidance can someone exercise
because they hate their body and they're
fat and disgusting and they need to
exercise as almost like a form of
bulimia right yeah totally I can eat and
throw up or I can eat and then go
exercise body hatred now
is is that radically different than
being grateful to be alive and get to
create and have experience and that all
of that only gets to happen because I
have a body and so I want to take good
care of this vessel that I'm in yeah
it's a totally different motivation
right and one of them happens after
binging and one of them happens just
because it's a good thing to do and you
know and one might happen so that I can
avoid feeling certain things and the
other one is happening just to support
feeling good in my body so the
motivation and how one relates to
anything can determine sex can be
addictive or it can be healthy and
healing meditation can be actually a way
to avoid dealing with real in one's
life yeah some people just get that and
float tanks as well it can they can be
incredibly powerful tools again tools or
if you spend like 10 hours a day and a
float tank what what exactly are you
doing that for well I see so many people
who will pray for world peace and not do
anything that actually tangibly makes
the world better and you know in a way
that is worse than not doing because it
if they didn't do it the pain of not
contributing to what they cared about
might make them find something actually
you know tangible they could do but the
reason they do that is because they
don't know what the to do about
climate change or about species
extinction it's too painful and they
can't do nothing and so that's something
they feel like they can do but it is
then importantly kind of a avoidance of
something rain the bypass of something
yeah exactly yeah there's I'm wondering
when so individual motivation is
important too but then we also have
individual biology and I wondered even
if you've tried to create the most
rounded
product in qualia they're still certain
person's specific rhythms and biology
that we can't overcome such as the times
of day where we enter flow state so I
know from what I've read and some of
your profiles online the you're
definitely a night owl and right now
we're talking it quite late night where
you are early morning I'm like my I feel
like I'm definitely a very low capacity
when I end up in like the the late night
is that something that can just an
example I guess of something that we
can't really change at the individual
level all right that was a few different
questions that I heard one is an is
qualia appropriate for everyone or do we
need personalized chemistry and then are
there things that we can't change with
our physiology and that needs to be
personalized so on the topic of
personalization first with word equality
its quality of the right chemistry for
everyone totally not it was the best
that we could do at making something
that worked for worked well for the most
people interested in that thing and it
was actually much better than I thought
we'd be able to do because you know my
background and starting to explore it
was based on full personalization so
working in integrative medical clinics
with you know different kinds of
innovative doctors helping design
customized
chemistry and neural chemistry support
but we got to actually see people's labs
see their qejy have the medical history
and and so I got to see how much we
could actually help people feel
radically better not just in terms of
cognitive enhancement but in terms of
their psychological being and yeah all
that I wasn't sure what we would be able
to do without personalization and I was
really curious because if there were
things that we could do that were
meaningful to wide audiences that
obviously would allow us to bring
support to a lot more people and the
cost of the personalization work was so
prohibitive
[Music]
so we were able to find that with there
are certain axes that are so sensitive
one person to the next or a different
kind of genetic clusters different
phenotypes that I just don't include
them in quality of won't use them in any
of our products so like for instance
you'll see we don't have folic acid
because whether you use folic acid or
you use some version of methylated folic
acid is there are so many people in each
of the groups and it makes such a big
difference whether they are over or
under methylating on that particular
axis that is just something without
personalization I don't mess with
because I because I couldn't actually do
it for a wide audience effectively and
so we work with axes that are pretty
commonly supported by the same things
for everybody the right krebs cycle
intermediaries that up greg you late ATP
production in that being pretty great
for everybody and for the people that
are seeking cognitive enhancement
supporting their acetylcholine
processing and supporting their
dopaminergic processing and then also
supporting neurogenesis and
synaptogenesis ends up being pretty
effective across the board and so those
are the ones that we work with now there
are still you know there's something
like 80% of the people that have tried
quality of it had a good response and
felt that it was meaningful for them and
something like half of those that it was
like life-changing the positive for and
other ones it was just you know
enhancing and then of the 20% that don't
have great experiences they're mostly
knoll experience they just don't
experience much of it yeah and that's
usually either because they have sleep
issues or digestive issues that we've
found in the tens of thousands of people
that have used it and given those
feedback so far and there are a few
people that don't and neither of those
are true and just not chemistry they
need so
where the person personalization is
right for everybody no but a lot of
people that's why we offer up you know
people can try it if it doesn't work
get your money back kind of thing now we
are working on rolling out a doctor
program right now where for people who
either do have real medical issues that
they want to address or real psychiatric
issues because we're not treating we're
not doing medicine we're just you know
providing enhancement tools or they want
to do enhancement that is customized
that we have doctors trained in
integrative medicine and the integrative
neuropsych and we're bringing additional
protocols to them that can actually help
test people and do really good work so
when you really good personalized work
so when you're asking how do you know
what good resources are we're working on
curating doctors that really can do a
good job of psychiatry and
psychopharmacology both you know and and
not just what we think of as psychiatry
but neurochemical optimization and that
would be cool in the meantime I would
say if people are interested the
integrative doctors it's it's hard
because some of them are awesome and
some of them are terrible but at least
the integrative doctors are working on
understanding personalization and root
cause in a deeper way than just what med
is going to be given for this symptom in
general the Institute for functional
medicine doctors seem to be getting
pretty well trained but finding finding
someone you actually like and resonate
with who'll spend time and it seems
knowledgeable is a is a valuable tool
yeah next part I'm sorry hon you gonna
do you want to respond to that or do you
want me to go on to the circadian
rhythms partner oh I'm definitely
interested in this Acadian rhythms yeah
where people start Katie
rhythms fixed or are they changeable
different opinions on this there is a
hypothesis that circadian rhythms are
have a strong genetic component and that
there are the morning larks the kind of
normal people and the night owls and
that you have give or take 70% of people
who have a normal circadian rhythm that
basically you know wakes in the in the
morning of light and about 15% of the
people that wake much earlier and 50% of
people to stay awake much later and the
evolution and biology story is that
there always had to be some people awake
in evolutionary environments for tribes
to be safe some Watchmen and that there
is a genetic predisposition to be in
those groups
I don't know how solid that is I know
there are some genes that are correlated
but we all obviously also know people
who were night I was when they were
teenagers or in college and now they
work a job where they wake up at 5:00
a.m. every day most people can adapt
their schedule fairly well most people
also if they control artificial lighting
and stimulants and exercise like that
most people do better on earlier
schedule than a later schedule no I'm
saying that at 1:00 a.m. my time yeah
it's like ass to me when I hop off here
I'm hopping on to another meeting the
rules of thumb like that are really good
starting places and then personal
exploration is important because I've
had very early schedules and later
schedules and I actually do better on
later schedule and so it is valuable for
people to explore what works best for
them well part of the underlying
question there is like it so it can be
changed potentially maybe maybe not but
also why why do we want to change it and
I think that can be down to the the
personal needs so if you're in a
relationship with someone
I experienced this in the past y-you
seem to be on the opposite timetables
that can be remarkably destructive and
can also seem to be a case that somebody
has to compromise for somebody else so
it can be much more personal as opposed
to simply you know put the practical
case of I need this kind of job
ya can be that mmm it can be someone
starts a spiritual practice where they
are in a meditation group at 4 a.m. I
think almost everybody when they have
kids gets a different sort ad and rhythm
than they had before because they are
gonna wake up whatever time their kids
come in so lots of lots of reasons there
but I will say getting enough sleep is
critical and in general also getting
enough light during the day is critical
and most people like I said do better if
they're waking up with with sunlight so
waking up in the dawn vicinity and then
getting an earlier bed and a regular
bedtime those are the general starting
recommendations that any sleep expert
will give you and and then like I said
some percentage of the people will find
that they do better or have personal
reasons like you said to do otherwise so
again we're back to the importance of
sleep in and of itself and we also
talked about how to get better nutrition
into our bodies when it comes to the the
other element that can make the
difference to absorbing these things
that was the the GI piece that you
mentioned and for those possibly
including me what are there some basic
steps to get a sense of if there is a
problem in the microbiome and what can
be done short of going into a specialist
lab which I think in most cases is not
immediately available or affordable are
there some steps that we can take
yeah so for most people there are
dietary things they can do that will
help their gut if they notice that they
are having GI symptoms they're having
gas or bloating or tenderness in their
abdomen or constipation or diarrhea or
upper GI issues acidity etc it gets
complex and the you know the allopathic
answer is to say you have IBD and which
can't you so many things not that that's
not that descriptive or useful right be
integrative approaches to the function
medicine approaches to try and figure
out what's going on and is it a food
allergy is it dysbiosis as it actually
pathogens bacteria parasite etcetera
many of which even when they're there
that the tests have a lot of false
negatives so it's kind of tricky to
figure it out
so the foundational things one can do
someone can do an elimination diet and
you can read online at how to do an
elimination diet where you eliminate the
foods that people commonly react to so
you eliminate the gluten grains the
dairy the soy corn and sugar and you
know but different people react to
different things so when you're doing
elimination diets there's different
things you can eliminate and then after
you know some period of time off of them
see do their symptoms get better if so
then reintroduce the foods one at a time
see which one kicks the symptoms on and
you start to get some insight this is a
way people can experiment on their own
with what foods your bothersome the ones
I mentioned are ones that are
classically bothersome for a lot of
people and there are people who have bad
GI reactions to plants to have leptin
sensitivities but you know the gluten
thing is obviously a very heated
controversial difficult topic for the
most part the gluten sensitivity the
food insensitive thing is not just a
marketing ploy and/or like a some weird
fad it is largely the result of Ubiquiti
IFAs 8 use on wheat and so it's not
actually gluten itself it's this
associated dynamic there's a law we
could get into there and there's a lot
of books that are critiquing grains and
why there are problems with grains the
paleo world is pretty big into this
where people can study further but there
are also a lot of people who leave the
u.s. go to Europe and find that they can
eat bread and pasta when they're in many
European countries and they come back
here and they can't and it actually does
have to do with different agricultural
methods in different countries so again
you can explore that topic but cutting
out hard to digest foods and foods you
might be reacting to and finding which
ones you react to is a first major step
some other steps that are worth noting
is not overeating it's kind of a major
step people are gonna have GI issues if
they're overeating or if they're eating
too fast or if they're not chewing well
eating too fast and not chewing well go
together and especially if people are on
the run or they're eating while they're
distracted and the the mechanical part
of digestion the actual chewing
investigation is really critical for the
chemical part of digestion to come later
because the acid and the enzymes are not
designed to break down large chunks of
food right they're designed to take
already tiny particles with a lot of
surface area and break them down further
so eating in a slower calm environment
healthier foods the right amount of them
chewing that's all a pretty big deal to
what's going in your GI tract drinking
enough water is actually quite important
so your GI tract can flush and
peristalsis is stimulated by water so
specifically drinking a lot of water
first thing in
morning like half a liter to a liter
first thing in the morning and then
waiting til that leaves your stomach
before having breakfast something like a
half hour very helpful for a lot of
people and then taking the right Pro and
prebiotics can be very helpful and the
prebiotics are foods that are gonna feed
the healthy bacteria in the gut and
there's a lot of prebiotics that people
can get into but just even starting
simply with things like resistance
starch just tight you know these are
kinds of fiber that helped feed good
bacteria differentially more than
bacteria that cause problems so a
prebiotic supplement taking it at night
in particular it's usually quite helpful
and you can take it with a probiotic and
probiotics are tricky this is also one
that you can personalize you can do an
test at home for your microbiome with
companies like biome or you biome and
see how your microbiome is doing and
start to personalize it you can do
deeper tests with integrative doctors
which be super useful so I won't get
into specific brands of probiotics but
there there are ones that can be quite
meaningful yeah there's a kind of taking
a lot of mental notes there and took a
swig of water whilst you were talking as
well has a lot of things to think about
and it's I guess something to emphasize
people listening that it's not just I
think a lot of nootropics are sort of in
terms of being for the mind and yet it's
really this connection this intimate
relationship between the mind and the
body and more and more it seems that
mental health issues such as depression
can be caused or exacerbated by the
things that are happening in the
microbiome and in the physical body I
guess we know at the superficial level
if you go and do some exercise you
probably feel better mentally and
emotionally but when we talk about diets
and so on I think not everyone is making
the the connection that there is a can
in between these things okay right
before we have done I was talking to a
friend who's just starting her first
business and she was asking me if I
would tell her just exactly what to do a
checklist for how to sort of business
and I said this is not the mindset
there's not the appropriate mindset to
sort of business is that's the
appropriate mindset to be an employee
which you've always been which is will
someone else tell me what to do and all
and I'll just do it right which is a
mindset that our parents and school and
religion trained us well to do but if
you're gonna run your own business then
you actually have to figure out what the
to do
you have to figure out what is relevant
what's needed does it make sense and
ultimately you're responsible for what
if your business fails because of
something your employees did it's still
your business that failed you're still
the one that hired those employees that
train them and manage them that you know
whatever it was and so and if your
business succeeds it's ultimately yours
right so the that the responsibility
well even more so when it comes to your
own health and when you if you coming
back to the beginning when you we're
talking about empowered responsibilities
in health every single experience that
we are going to have in this life is
going to be mediated through our body
every experience of learning and helping
people and making love and staring a
sunset and you know every everything
what we're going to do is going to be
mediated through our physiology and how
long it lasts and how vital it is and
how cognitively clear we are how
emotionally clear we are is it is all
related to the bio hardware that our
consciousness is running on and so
you're born here you got this body you
didn't happen to have an education
manual given to you for how to really
use it well but you should
figure it out
like of all the things that everyone
should become an expert in learning how
to take care of the vessel that they
exist in that mediates everything else
they do should be one of the things that
everybody develops some capacity in yeah
I guess because we all have one we take
it so for granted that we forget that
it's it's the thing that's so important
than ever present that it's easy to
overlook as you say we people get rid of
houses and get new ones they get rid of
cars and get new ones you cannot live
with your body no yet you have to take
care of it yes you say that brings us
around full circle to responsibility and
I want to be respectful of your time I
feel like I would happily sit through
your sleep cycle way for you to wake up
and keep talking and just go round and
round and round but we can wrap things
up on four for this particular occasion
d there's just one more question we
didn't ask you last time but we like to
ask the guest and I think in the context
of this conversation I think there
should be if it's very fitting and that
is what does living a high existence
mean to you hmm
well there's obviously lots of really
fun ways to answer that Oh
share one answer that's related to
something we talked about today which
was you were asking the question of can
we enhance certain capabilities without
detracting from other ones can we
increase our ability to focus on a task
and do task switching simultaneously
we're we're used to doing a lot of
theory of trade-offs in our life where
at all scales what's good for one
country is bad for another country in
terms of war particular trade agreement
or whatever what's good for one company
is bad for another company that's
competing in space
what's good what seems like it's good
for us today is actually bad
tomorrow in terms of the chocolate cake
scenarios that we were talking about or
the the smart drug we're using that
seems good for one aspect of life is
actually damaging other aspects of life
the the proposal that we're voting on is
it leads to so much political
polarization is because it benefits some
things and damages others and so people
who care about one side cluster here
those a cluster there as much as we can
get over decision making based on
unnecessary dichotomy is an unnecessary
theory of trade-offs and say how can we
factor everything that is connected to
it all the things that are
interconnected to a particular decision
that are meaningful and enhance them all
simultaneously right enhance across
dialectics simultaneously so is there a
way to help the economy make jobs and
make the environment better rather than
jobs or the environment well there are
and if you require that you find
something that does both life is gonna
be radically better can we find
something that helps task switching and
focus yes and now that starts to extend
to everything can I live my life in a
way that is actually enjoyable now and
that leads to a progressively more
enjoyable future
yes can I figure out how to increase my
gratitude what is while simultaneously
increasing my motivation to make things
better yes so all of the dichotomies
where we will typically enhance one
thing at the cost of something else
meaningful you know we could say a high
existence is being high in any
particular area but most of the things
that people would try to make higher
they would try to optimize would be at
the expense of something else in the in
the tree that previous way of thinking
about it so high across all domains
simultaneously because we're thinking
about the interconnectedness of all of
it and supporting the entire picture or
consciously
is that one meaningful way to think
about hi existence yeah I think that's
the most healthy way in which to try and
approach it that we live in so many
times we seem to think we're we're
living in a world of zero-sum games but
what I like the what you're emphasizing
which is that if we begin from the
premise of how can we find the best
thing that includes all of these
elements rather than thinking I just
want to go down one particular rabbit
hole thank you thank you for that and
thank you for coming on the show again
and sharing a lot of very deep knowledge
that certainly got me thinking that I
need to go and pursue some elimination
diet and maybe not keep buying
cheesecake I mean it's cheesecake
Russian chocolate cake it's my
particular fascination so people can
find links and everything to bring neuro
hacker collective in the shownotes but
that's where to find you and we've
linked up with you to create a
promotional offer for qualia that I give
the full details and the intro to this
episode and as you said there's it's not
a risk to check it out and that people
can try it and see if it does work for
them but it seems very likely that it
will it was a delight to be here with
you and I'm happy to come back again if
listeners have questions in particular
they'd like to go in a particular
direction so if so let me know
absolutely that would be awesome so if
you're listening you've got questions
you want to ask Daniel then get in touch
with us and you can leave comments at
the bottom of the post or on Facebook
whatever we'll be paying attention to
that and yeah all the more reason to
have another mind opening conversation
so thanks again Daniel and until next
time I hope that we can all try and
pursue living a higher existence thank
you John
thanks for listening if you appreciate
the high existence podcast the best way
to support it is to invest in yourself
by acquiring one or more of our self
development tools at story existence com
use the code wisdom and check out to get
a huge twenty five percent off the
thirty challenges to enlightenment
course you can also leave reviews on
iTunes or share it with your friends on
social media thank you so much for
tuning in and cheers to a high existence
[Music]
[Applause]